בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is ס"א Samech Aleph 61,
we start a new פרק perek המוכר את הבית, Hamocher Et Habayit,
and this פרק perek is going to be much more I guess
I would say concrete than the previous one in that it's not,
you know the previous one was a lot of abstract concepts about
חזקה Chazaka and proof and עדות Eidut and all these different issues.
This is going to be like when you say you're selling your
house, what's included in the house? When you say you're selling a
cow or whatever, a horse, what's included? Okay, if you don't specify
otherwise. So it's a very interesting type of a shift. I do
want to say, you know the one sentence because we sort of
had to rush through the end yesterday, you know the אגדתא Agadeta
at the end. I mean it certainly was very disturbing, you know
because it sort of, it ended with a balance. I mean it's
right before the end there was a nice balance of like we
have to have אבלות aveilus on the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash but
we have to sort of live our life, you can live your
life like you know fully, you know you don't have to live
your life in mourning, you know not maybe not a hundred percent,
so 99 percent you do a little זכר zeicher but you know
but you're not sort of obsessing in the mourning and then in
the end it sort of struck back that tone of like yeah
really we should just close up shop completely. But anyway so I
don't know what to say about that. But what I do want
to say is it's an interesting אגדתא Agadeta in general at the
end, you know the entire פרק perek is about חזקת הבתים Chezkas
Habatim so to show a certain type of a permanence of ownership
right? It's all about saying this is my land right and proving
it's my land. I've been here three years and I have a
right to it. And if you think about it right at the
very beginning of the פרק perek one of the ideas about the
idea of a חזקה Chazaka right and proving whether you had a
שטר shtar or not was from the נבואה nevua in ירמיה, Yirmiyah,
I don't know if people remember that it said right the, I
don't know that said you know go ahead and write שטרות shtaros
and put them in a כלי חרס kli cheres למען יעמדו ימים
רבים, lema'an ya'amdu yamim rabbim, you know you're going into גלות golus
and so on. So it's about like you know your, you're now
going to be living in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz you know in
גלות golus or whatever and like who knows when you're going to
get back to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So I think that that's
like an interesting רמז. remez. All of these heavy discussions about proving
whose land it is, this is all חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz you
know, this is all not where we belong, this is all really
not where we should be living. We have to sort de remembering
when you build your house you leave a little זכר לחורבן, zeicher
l'churban,
you know and I think particularly, I mean על כל פנים al
kol panim the original teaching was in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
you know but particularly in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz all that sense
of land and homes and whatever like remember this is not where
the permanence is and this is not
where like we should what? אם לא אעלה את ירושלים. Im lo
a'aleh es Yerushalayim.
Yeah
right, that's exactly the verse that was quoted. But I'm saying, but
I'm saying that I think that's particularly a reason after such a
long and intense פרק perek you know chapter which is all about
that sense of owning and proving ownership and it's done through a
sense of semi-permanence to sort of remind us that this is not
our permanent place you know.
Well that's true also. Let's go on to the, let's go, yes
Rabbi Dov.
What, what did you understand at the very very end of the
אגדתא?
Agadeta? I didn't. I didn't. Okay המוכר Hamocher what?
Yeah, the end was I can't deal with the last two sentences
of that, like that just was such a such a sort of
a an almost like this nihilistic type of a note I don't
know what to do with that. But the, but before that it
was a very I thought you know the type of balance that
we actually go by right? Live a full life but remember אם
לא אעלה את ירושלים על ראש שמחתנו. im lo a'aleh es Yerushalayim
al rosh simchasenu. Okay
so let's go on and begin the next פרק. perek. Joe, welcome.
I understand Joe is here it's your יארצייט yahrtzeit for your father's
יארצייט. yahrtzeit. What was his name? חנוך בן הרש
לייב.
Chanoch ben Hersh
Leib. הרש לייב, Hersh Leib, הרש לייב. Hersh Leib. הרש לייב, Hersh
Leib, okay. May his נשמה neshama have an עליה. aliyah. Alright let's
start now the new פרק perek המוכר את הבית. Hamocher Es Habayis.
So somebody sells the house. What's included in the sale right? You
draw up a bill of sale says I'm selling you my house
and now the person what do you mean by house? What's included?
So לא מכר יציע. lo machar yetzia. So you do not sell
the יציע, yetzia, the, the,
I looked up the English word for this, it's veranda. You don't
sell the veranda. That seems to be what we're talking about. A
type of like a porch, I mean we'll see in the גמרא,
Gemara, the גמרא Gemara also seems like יציע yetzia might actually be
like a room that is attached to the house, like an exterior
room. Yes what's it?
יציעות yetzia'os in סוכה? Sukkah? Yeah what is it, a balcony? You
mean? Yeah so right but here it doesn't seem like it's an
interior balcony. It seems like it's an exterior to the wall of
the house okay? Either it's a type of a porch with an
enclosed porch like a veranda or a semi-open porch, we'll see in
a minute or just some type of a of an add-on but
it's built exterior to the house. Okay. Some type of a like,
you know, I don't know, a shed that's attached to the house.
You mean you need to go through this room therefore to get
into the house?
Yeah, I mean it's very bizarre. Like, to me this whole משנה
Mishnah is very bizarre. Like, somebody's going to own the veranda and
someone else is going to own the house? Like, I understand the
idea that you could say the word house doesn't necessarily include that,
but like to think that that means that I'm going to hold
on to ownership of that when I'm selling you the house is
a strange idea. Anyway,
let's read a little bit. Okay, לא מכר יציע. Lo machar yatzia.
ואף על פי שפתוחה לתוכה, Ve-af al pi she-p'tucha le-tocha, right, even
though
the basically the this veranda opens into the house and maybe, who
knows, maybe the only way to get to the veranda is through
the house, we're going to see in a minute, so you would
think like of course like it has to it doesn't exist separate
from the house. No, it's not part of the house. ולא את
החדר שלפנים הימנו. Ve-lo et hacheder she-liphnim heimenu. Not only that, if
you have an interior room in the house, okay, that's not included
as well. Now this is also like wild. Like, what does that
mean an interior room? I've got a three-bedroom apartment, I'm not selling
my bedrooms? So apparently it seems like you know because we've seen
before like an idea of an inner room which really means sort
of like an like something that could exist as a separate domicile.
You know, that's what I would say. Well, right, the mother-in-law suite,
something like that, right. So anyway, so you basically have the front
of the house that's got your kitchen and your living room and
your bedroom or whatever it is. And then there's a door to
a back section that has its own little living space. Now if
you said that, that makes a lot of sense, although not some
degree it makes sense, some degree not really because the purpose of
that separate living space, you know, at least we would think it
would be for the for the use of the person who owns
the house. But we have seen before the idea that one person
owns the ground floor, one person owns the top floor, one person
owns the front, one person owns the back. Condominium? Right, so anyway,
although the access to the back is only through the front. Alright,
but so to the degree that it would be normal for a
different person to own the back, that could make a lot of
sense. But I will say that's how I would have explained the
word חדר Cheder here, but I will say the רשב"ם Rashbam explains
it in a way that I really don't understand. If you look
at the רשב"ם Rashbam on חדר, Cheder, four lines down, אף על
פי שהוא לפנים מן הבית ופתוח לתוכו
ודריסתם לבית. Af al pi shehu liphnim min habayit u-p'tuach le-tocho ve-drisatam
labayit. Now so far that could work with my explanation. בית Bayit
meaning like a separate type of a of a living
of a living space. דכיון
דאינו עשוי אלא להצניע שם חפציו
לשמור כמו בתיבה הלכך אינו בכלל בית.
De-keivan de-eino asui ela lehatznia sham chafatzav lishmor
k'mo
betevah hilkach eino biklal bayit. Sounds like it's like an attic, right,
a storage room, an attic, okay, so like so okay, I'm going
to sell you my house and I'm keeping the attic? I'm keeping
the you know the storage room in the back? So it's very
strange like that this would be considered separate. I really don't understand
a lot of this.
Okay, so a person might have all their belongings that they don't
want they need some space.
Alright, in that case where I still have all my belongings there,
right, if that were the case, but we're not limiting it to
that case, we're doing it because we're basically saying oh that's not
an essential part of the house. That's, you know, ולא את הגג
בזמן שיש לו מעקה גבוה עשרה טפחים. Ve-lo et hagag bizman she-yesh
lo ma'akeh gavoah asara tefachim. If your roof has a has a
you know a gate around it, which you know you would think
it would need to because of the הלכה, halacha, the מצוה mitzvah
of עשית מעקה לגגך, Asita ma'akeh l'gagecha, okay, we'll discuss that. But
anyway, but then it's a separate living space, right, you know like
in Manhattan, right, or in Brooklyn or whatever, you know people do
like you know the roof for these buildings they have these garden
parties or whatever, you know it's this great like living space up
there. Alright, so I mean like depends that it's not raining or
too cold.
And you can say you can't go through my house to get
to yours.
Well, that's a good point, right, how do you get access to
it? But again, the funny thing is like I understand that all
of these are nice usable spaces, but to think that like to
you know that that ownership would be split. Now again, maybe I'm
thinking too much like in the New York context, like I remember
that I was in the Old City, in the Old City in
Israel, and you go to a certain part of the Old City
and you're walking on like all this concrete and it looks like
totally like just a flat big expanse of concrete and what you
realize is you're walking on the roofs of all the houses below,
but from where you're standing you don't even realize it's like rooftops,
right? It's like these concrete playgrounds or what you know playgrounds or
whatever it might be. But it still is interesting that not only
is it seen as can have an independent existence but like you
assume that the seller is still holding on to it even when
he's transferring the house. Yes.
Is it possible that it's something a little bit simpler? Like of
course you acquire all these other aspects because they're all attached, but
the price of the house, when I say the house is ten
thousand dollars, it's not all these other things.
No, I mean yeah, no, yeah, that's not what we're saying. I
mean we are going to have to deal with how do you
look at what was sold for to determine what was included, but
the point the question always is is like is like what actually
transferred during the sale? That's really the that's always the consistent question.
I mean I hear your attempt. I mean I'm grappling with this
too. I mean we'll keep on reading.
What about a car, oh air conditioning?
Right, right, right, right, right. I'm keeping the tires. I'm keeping the
tires. Yeah, exactly. I get better resale value, the tires. You know,
they detach from the car.
Yes. Exactly, exactly. This is why I think it's so hard to
teach history, because it's very hard to understand something minus the culture
and the
life, poverty, strength, value. I mean, maybe in that world, it isn't
so unusual to have these kinds of understandings.
It must be, you know. So let's keep on going and hopefully
some of this will clarify itself. Or not. רבי יהודה אומר אם
יש צורת הפתח אף על פי שאינה גבוהה עשרה טפחים אינו מכור.
Rabbi Yehuda omer im yesh tzurat hapetach af al pi she'eina gevoha
asara tefachim eino machur. If the fence around the roof has a...
has like a, you know, a צורת הפתח, tzurat hapetach, a doorway
type of a structure, then you're clearly recognizing it as its own
separate living space and then it doesn't need to have a fence
עשרה טפחים. asara tefachim. Okay, let's take a look at the Gemara.
מאי יציאה? mai yitzia? What is this veranda or this add-on roof?
הכא תרגימו אפתא. hacha targimu afta. Here in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
they translate it as אפתא. afta. You might remember that word came
up yesterday when we spoke about splitting the house. Okay.
And look at the Rashbam, afantimen, whatever that is, בנין נמוך אצל
הבית מצדו או מאחוריו. binyan namuch eitzel habayit mitzido o me'achorav. Some
type of a structure built... what? Apartment? Built onto the house. The
wall of the house. Okay. רב יוסף אמר בדקא חלילא. Rav Yosef
amar bidka chalila. So
בדקא חלילא bidka chalila is like a... a latticed type of a
veranda. It's similarly like some built-on structure, but as opposed to enclosed
walls, it has more walls, you know, that have... that are more
open with like pillars or lattice and let the air come in.
Okay. למאן דאמר אפתא לא מזדבנה, leman de'amar afta lo mizdavna, if
you say you don't even sell this enclosed veranda or this enclosed
room that's added on, כל שכן בדקא חלילא לא מזדבנה, kol sheken
bidka chalila lo mizdavna, certainly this like... this latticed veranda because that's...
would not be sold. Because a... yeah. What?
A portico, right? A portico.
Yeah, but a portico, but this is like just a veranda of
a house. I mean, a portico stands by itself. What?
Called an attic in this...
an attic? Yeah. Here... well, a veranda would go all the way
around, right? A veranda would be... here's your house, right, and here's
like the... the porch in front of your house. But what it
actually... you know, you know like people have like a nice like...
you know, where they sit and they... and they sip lemonade or
whatever. Okay. But what it sounds... but it sounds more what we're
talking about is if that's... this is your house or whatever, that
we're talking about some type of a... of a like a little
add-on that's done like there, something of that nature. That's certainly the
פסוקים pesukim we're about to quote from the נביאים nevi'im is going
to sound like that. בדקא חלילא. bidka chalila. Yeah. Then the question
is, is it fully enclosed or does it have... or is it
more like open-aired type of a thing? Okay. That says an attic,
Bobby?
It says here... yeah... that the אפתא... afta... yeah... is interpreted
as an attic and then רב יוסף Rav Yosef said it means
a windowed structure and that's the בדקא... bidka... yeah.
So I don't know about attic. That's not the way the Rashbam
or it's not the פסוקים pesukim that we're about to quote. It
sounds like we're more talking about something that's immediately attached.
Okay. I see it translated as a veranda and according to this
ArtScroll translation, actually.
Veranda? Yeah. Anyway, it's certainly whether it's a veranda like this, a
porch that goes all the way around or it's just some built-on
structure, from the... we're about to quote פסוקים pesukim in נך Nach
that make it sound clearly that it's a built-on structure. Okay. So
it's something of that nature.
So the Gemara says like this: למאן דאמר אפתא לא מזדבנה, leman
de'amar afta lo mizdavna, if the אפתא afta isn't sold together with
it because it's independent,
כל שכן בדקא חלילא, kol sheken bidka chalila, certainly this type of
a latticed thing is... is... is... is... is independent because it's not
just like an extension of the house, right? It's a different type
of a thing. It's got its... its latticed walls. It's not like
a... a fully enclosed space like the house. אבל למאן דאמר בדקא
חלילא, aval leman de'amar bidka chalila, but if you say that this
is referring to some type of a latticed, you know, extension, אבל
אפתא מזדבנה, aval afta mizdavna, but if it was enclosed add-on, then
it would be sold. That would just be seen as an extension
of the house. Okay. תני רב יוסף, tani Rav Yosef, so רב
יוסף Rav Yosef taught: שלשה שמות יש לו. shelosha shemot yesh lo.
This יציאה yitzia has three names.
Okay.
יציאה, צלע, ותא. yitzia, tzeila, veta. So תא ta means a box,
and a יציאה yitzia and a צלע. tzeila. צלע tzeila is like
a... what? תא? ta? Okay, תא. ta.
So יציאה דכתיב היציאה התחתונה חמש באמה רחבה. yitzia dichtiv hayitzia hatachtona
chamesh ba'ama rachava. Okay. So this is talking about when they built
the wall of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. It says that...
right, so it says basically you have these walls around the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, okay, and then it says on these walls they
built these types of יציאות, yitziot, which are basically these... these types
of like chambers exterior to the walls. And actually, the way the
פסוקים pesukim say is that they built it... the first one was
narrow... you would think that if you're building multiple ones storied, that
the... the bottom one is going to be wider. But actually the
פסוקים pesukim say that there were three and as they went up
they got wider. wider. Why?
Because the wall of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, this is a
side view, the wall of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, right, here's
the wall, here's the thickness of the wall, whatever, anyway the wall
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash was built with with you know
it sort of indentation, yeah, like indentations. So the wall the base
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash wall, I guess it would have
been better if it was different colors, but anyway the base of
the מקדש Mikdash wall looked like that. So the so the add-ons
looked like that. Now why they do that as the base of
the wall, well the way at least the רשב"ם Rashbam explains was
was that it's so that you could sort of support the add-on
here. They were made poles to support the roof of the add-on
and that's the way they did it that way. But anyway but
that's what it says. It says they built
these these יציאות, ytzi'ot, these sort of exterior types of chambers to
outside of the wall of the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. היציע התחתונה חמש באמה רחבה. Hatzaya hatachtona chamesh
ba'ama rechava. צלע דכתיב והצלעות צלע אל צלע שלוש ושלושים פעמים. Tzela
dechtiv vehatzela'ot tzela el tzela shalosh ushloshim pa'amim. Okay so this is
in יחזקאל Yechezkel when it describes the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. And
as we all know the description in יחזקאל Yechezkel are quite different
than other descriptions about what the structure looked like and what the
קרבנות korbanot looked like, but nevertheless it's describing a similar phenomenon, these
exterior types of chambers that are exterior to the wall of the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash except rather than having three it has like
thirty three. So I don't know what to say about that. But
anyway but they're all describing these exterior chambers built on to the
exterior wall of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. תא דכתיב והתא קנה
אחד אורך וקנה אחד רוחב ובין התאים חמש אמות. Ta dechtiv vehata
kaneh echad orech vekaneh echad rochav uvein hata'im chamesh amot. So this
is also a פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל Yechezkel describing these sort of
exterior chambers and different types of dimensions but these are all these
chambers that are built onto the exterior wall of the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. Okay ואי בעית אימא מהכא. Ve'ibayis eima mehacha. And if
you want I can show you from a from a משנה mishna
because maybe you think oh like that this word תא ta describing
this and again we're sticking with the structure of
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. But it says כותל ההיכל שש והתא
שש כותל
התא חמש אמה. Kotel haheichal shesh vehata shesh
kotel hata chamesh
ama. So basically if you have the היכל, heichal,
alright, so like the structure you you have the אולם ulam
in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash with the היכל, heichal, the היכל
heichal is where the מנורה menorah and the שולחן shulchan were. Am
I drawing these on the right side? Let's see. If this is
east? No.
This is north. So I'm on the wrong side. Okay anyway whatever
there's that, that's the היכל, heichal, that's the
דביר. dvir. Okay anyway alright so that's the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Anyway so it says so the so this says so what does
it say? כותל ההיכל שש, Kotel haheichal shesh, the thickness of this
wall was six, okay, six
six אמות. amot. והתא שש Vehata shesh and then you had a
six אמה ama
chambers built onto that so that onto the thickness of the wall.
And then
כותל where was it? וכותל התא חמש and then the thickness of
that exterior wall was five. Okay so anyway but what you're just
seeing is is that it's just describing that these תא ta is
a יציע yatzia or צלע tzela are these exterior chambers built on
you know to the exterior wall. Okay yeah.
So Charlie how can we use פסוקים psukim from יחזקאל Yechezkel to
describe the בית המקדש?
Beis Hamikdash? Well we're just showing you that I mean all these
three פסוקים psukim and the משנה mishna in מידות Middot are all
describing the same phenomenon that in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash you
had these exterior chambers. Right and it's just showing that we use
the similar... we're not trying to resolve the problematics of יחזקאל. Yechezkel.
We're just trying to show that they're describing a similar structure.
Yeah. These exterior chambers shall I say presumably they didn't have the
same קדושה kedusha as the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash?
Not necessarily. No. I mean that's always a question about the thickness
of the wall whatever.
Anyway for instance if you were מוכר mocher the בית bayis you're
not מוכר mocher the יציע yatzia so it should be something independent.
Oh you mean yeah well maybe but okay that's a good point
actually. How much does this connect with this question those questions of
קדושה? kedusha? But the other thing I do want to say is
that look at this. Once again we are referencing like the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So it's actually right quite fascinating. And actually it
just occurs to me we started at the very beginning... I was
about to say it just occurs to me the whole issue about
the building of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash came in like right
exactly right as the building. You're you're building a wall and all
of this. So it does seem that that's also connected to the
theme of the end of the last פרק. perek. You know here
you are now of course the משנה mishna was written in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael but it was still post חורבן. churban. But nevertheless
thinking about all that sense that we're having buildings and structures or
whatever and thinking about what it echoes in terms of you know
this type of a בית bayis but then there was the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash right?
The textual paradigm is the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. There is no
such thing as a בית... bayis... right...
taking the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Right, yeah. Okay so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר מר זוטרא והוא דחזי. Amar Mar
Zutra vehu dehazei. I know, I agree. והוא דחזי... Vehu dehazei... והוא
דהוה ארבע אמות. v'hu d'havei arba amos. Okay, this idea that it
would be considered its own identity, its own separate thing and not
all together, is that it would have to be ארבע אמות arba
amos by four
amot, at least. Less than that, it would be completely trivial and
an add-on to the
house. It wouldn't have an independent standing. אמר ליה רבינא למר זוטרא.
Amar lei Ravina l'Mar Zutra. So Ravina said to Mar Zutra, לדידך
דאמרת דהוי ארבע אמות, l'didach d'amart d'havei arba amos, you say it
needs to be four amot, אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, גבי בור, gabi
bor, we're going to come up saying also if you sell the
house you don't sell like the well even if there's a well
right near that serves as the water for the house. דתנן, d'tnan,
and a Mishna is going to say coming up in a few
daf, לא את הבור ולא את הדות, lo es habor v'lo es
hados, if you sell the house you do not sell with it
the well or the dos which is the cistern like something you
know built above ground. אף על פי שכתב לו עומקא ורומא, af
al pi she'kasav lo umka v'ruma, even if in your bill of
sale you're saying I am selling you the house including all the
air space and all of the like what's it called mineral rights
or whatever all of the property rights go all the way down
and all the way up. Very nice. All the way down and
all the way up on the footprint of the
house. But that doesn't mean you're selling the well that's not part
of the footprint that's not you know there in the space of
the house. That's the Mishna. Okay, so how is that relevant? So
he says, אי הוי ארבע אמות אין ואי לא לא, ei havei
arba amos in v'ei lo lo, do you say that also there
it's only independent if it's four amot, less than four amot it's
not independent and it goes with the house? And presumably part of
the question the way the Rashbam explains it is and a standard
bor would not necessarily be four amot wide, certainly not a private
bor for a house. So really? So you think everything has to
be four amot to be independent? So the answer is like apples
and oranges. The answer is, מר Mar says, no, הכי השתא, hachi
hashta, what type of a question is that? התם הא תשמישתא לחוד
והא תשמישתא לחוד. hasam ha tashmishta l'chud v'ha tashmishta l'chud.
By the case of the house and the well, each one serves
a completely separate function. Nobody thinks a house is an extension of
a well or a well is an extension of a house. I
mean it's used with the house but it's not part it's not
like they do separate things. One goes down, one goes down underground
and you get water from it, the other is on the ground
and you live in it. Okay, so those are separate things. הכא
אידי ואידי חד תשמישתא היא. hacha idi v'idi chad tashmishta hi. Here
they're all the same thing, they're enclosed spaces that you're living in
and the only question is is it one space or is it
two spaces? So אי הוי ארבע אמות חשיב ואי לא לא חשיב.
ei havei arba amos chashiv v'ei lo lo chashiv. By four amot
it's its own space and if it's not it's an extension of
the space of the house which makes you know a lot of
sense. And again to the degree that these are spaces which you
could access independently, right? Like you know you don't have to access
through the house, if I really had an exterior access to it
I would understand this. You know but the more these are spaces
that are only accessed like through the house, again it's just in
my mind it's harder to understand that when I'm selling you the
house I'm still keeping ownership of that, but the Gemara is saying
is to the degree that it can exist and function as its
own space unless you're explicit about it it does not go with
it.
Yes there's a Mishna coming up since you now mentioned things like
bor whatever, what about like your front yard and back yard, but
that is included?
So we'll see about all that. Also a lot of times they
wouldn't have their own front yard back yard it would be part
of a חצר. chatzer. All right, right and this whole perek is
about it. ולא את החדר שלפנים ממנו v'lo es hachedar shelifnim mimenu
and not the interior room. Now again the Rashbam tells the interior
room sounds like a storage room. I would have thought it meant
like a separate like you know living facility. But anyway the Gemara
says like this. השתא יציע לא מיזדבן חדר מיבעיא. hashta yatzia lo
mizdaban chedar mibaya. If you're not going to sell a יציע yatzia
this add-on you know this add-on structure, so that's going to be
seen as independent, of course a separate room will be independent. Now
again the way I would explain it is of course if you
really had an inner חדר chedar which was often could have been
owned or lived by a different in by a different person, you
know different tenants, so of course that's independent that's not just some
type of a functional add-on type of a room that's a really
independent living space. All right so that's at least the way I
understand the question. Anyway let's see what the Gemara says. לא צריכא
דאף על גב. lo tzaricha d'af al gav. You're right. It should
be obvious that the house does not include this inner this inner
living space. But the case you need to tell me this is
דאף על גב דמצריה למיצרא אבראי. d'af al gav d'matzrei l'metzra abra'i.
Now this is really a shocker okay which is you basically say,
here's my house, here's the footprint of my house, okay here's the
main part, right here's the bedroom, here's my little living room, here's
my kitchen, I don't know why I'm talking about my tea kettle
in my kitchen whatever it is. Okay here's my thing and then
here is my back thing here, okay you know the separate living
quarters. Okay you really don't understand? והיכא דשייר.
v'heicha d'shayer. That's the wall.
Okay oh you mean here? Yeah it's an open living space. Anyway
fine. Anyway whether this is a storage facility like the Rashbam says
and whether it's like a totally separate like living space, either way
that's the inner room. So the Gemara says obviously it's a separate
living space, of course it's not assumed to be included you know
with this. So what the Gemara says no no no what we
needed to tell you is that in the document you wrote I
am selling you my house and my house runs like a hundred
feet to the you know to the you know to the... to
the east and you know 300 feet in you know to the
whatever to the north, and these are the dimensions of my house,
and in the document you gave the exterior dimensions, so which includes
the exterior dimensions obviously include this. No, you didn't include that. It's
crazy. How could you say that wasn't included? So let's take a
look. אעגב דמצר ליה מצרי בראי, af gav dematzar lei metzarei barai,
I would just say with all of this like I'm just reading
it, okay?
I have as much problem understanding this as all of you, yes.
Alright, let's just finish reading the statement, okay? דאעגב דמצר ליה מצרי
בראי de-af gav dematzar lei metzarei barai even though you draw the
exterior boundaries. כרב נחמן, ke-Rav Nachman, like Rav Nachman says, דאמר רב
נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, de-amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha,
המוכר בית לחבירו בבירה גדולה, ha-mocher bayit le-chavero be-birah gedolah, if you
sell a chamber or a house in a large castle. Now the
way the רשבם Rashbam actually explains the word בירה birah actually is
like a castle. The רשבם Rashbam says, I don't know if people
have ever visited some of these castles, I don't know, I don't
have a lot of בקיאות bekiut in it, but if you go
inside of a castle there's this like large open space in the
middle, right, and you know and then I'm not going to be
good here with my drawings, but anyway, there's this large like grassy
space in the middle and then there are off around it there
are all of these various like you know rooms and living quarters,
right? So anyway, so imagine you had something like that, this was
a whole enclosed castle and you had all of these various, I
mean actually there's some places here in Riverdale like this that they
you know like a shared green space, right, but anyway but it
was all contained within like one structure, one physical wall, one physical
structure and you have like separate houses here that all kind of
share that shared courtyard. Okay, so he says I'm selling Jenna here,
I own this one chamber house within this castle complex and I'm
going to sell it to Jenna, I'm saying I'm selling you my
house, okay? And when I describe the dimensions of my house I
say, I am selling you my בית bayit and I draw and
I say and here are the dimensions and I draw the exterior
wall of the castle. Okay, so let's take a look. המוכר בית
לחבירו בבירה גדולה אעפ שמיצר לו מצרים החיצוניים, ha-mocher bayit le-chavero be-birah
gedolah af al pi she-metzar lo metzarim ha-chitzoniyim, even though you bounded
it and you give the exterior dimensions, so מצרים הרחיב לו, metzarim
hirchiv lo, I'm just broadening the boundaries but I'm not really selling
it to you. What does that mean, I'm expanding the
boundaries? Right, it would only be a question if I owned the
castle. If I didn't own the castle of course I couldn't sell
it, I can't sell something I don't own, what? So presumably I
owned the whole thing but I'm living here, maybe I'm a realtor,
I own the whole thing and I you know, but whatever it
is, but the funny thing is like what does that mean? So
the way the רשבם, Rashbam, so yeah so the way the רשבם
Rashbam explains it is, well let's read the way the רשבם Rashbam
explains it, see if you can understand it better than I can.
He says like this, בבירה גדולה be-birah gedolah is that what
you
want?
Yeah, no he doesn't really,
yeah well let's, yeah he doesn't really explain it. Later the גמרא
Gemara is going to explain that in some case, oh yeah yeah
כרב נחמן, ke-Rav Nachman, that's the one, the first narrow line. שלא
ידע לפרש ולאו מחדר שלי היא ממערבה של בית דאין זה מצר
הניכר לאנשי העיר והוא ככתב מצרים הניכרים. shelo yada lefaresh velav mechader
sheli hi mima'arava shel bayit de'ein zeh metzar hanikar le'anshei ha'ir vehu
ke-katav metzarim hanikarim. Like if you said I'm selling you my house,
nobody, it's not identifiable, so you gave the dimensions of the castle
so everybody says oh yeah he sold you a place in that
castle, okay? But that's like still, it's bizarre. Why don't you say
I'm selling you a house in the castle and here's the dimensions
of the castle? It's the thing he actually says I'm selling you
a house and here are the dimensions and then we're supposed to,
like even if it's hard to identify the house and it's easy
to identify the castle, it still seems very bizarre that we should
interpret it that way.
Yes, I don't know, so like everybody else I'm not like sure
but,
like in the Middle East it's like you build a house, it's
flat roof, then you build a thing on top of it for
the kids and you build a thing in the back and you
build a, in other words there's not like it's not like here.
Right. So like maybe that's part of the concept that they're working
with, the reality is like okay I'm looking at this big structure,
it's got all these pieces to it. Right.
But if you're drawing the outside boundaries,
I'm going back in.
I understand, let's read a little more of the גמרא, Gemara, maybe
we can all figure it out together, okay? Not like I prepared
last night, I just don't understand it. Alright, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this. היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אילימא דקרו
לבית בית ולבירה בירה, ilima dekaro le-bayit bayit u-le-birah birah, if they
have different names for it, the room is called a בית bayit
and the whole complex is called a בירה, birah, פשיטא, peshita, בית
זבן ליה בירה לא זבן ליה. bayit zavan lei birah lo zavan
lei. Even if you give the dimensions, if you say I'm selling
you a room and here are the dimensions and you give a
dimension of the castle, clearly you ignore the dimensions because that's not
what the word room means. Alright, so even that's not so פשוט,
pashut, why should you go by the labeling more than by the
you know dimensions? But okay, if the labeling is clear, clear. That
will beat out the dimensions and you sold only the room and
not the whole castle. אלא, Ella, פשיטא בית זבין ליה בירה לא
זבין ליה. pshita bayis zavin lei bira lo zavin lei. אלא, Ella,
דלבירה נמי קרי ליה בית. de-libira nami kare lei bayis. So sometimes
no, maybe sometimes the word בית bayis can refer to the whole
castle. So if that's true, כולה זבין ליה. kula zavin lei. So
if the word בית bayis can refer to the whole castle and
you gave those dimensions, that's what you sold. No, לא צריכא, lo
tzricha, here would be the case where what we're talking
about, דרובא קרי ליה לבית בית ולבירה בירה. de-rubba kare lei le-bayis
bayis u-le-bira bira. Most people when they want to refer to the
castle only use the word בירה, bira, they don't use the word
בית. bayis. דאיכא נמי דלבירה קרי בית. de-ika nami de-libira kare bayis.
And there's a small percentage of the population that when they want
to talk about the castle they say my house. Come to my
house, I got a small little house in Connecticut, okay. Same exact
phenomenon on המניח את הכד. ha-maniach es ha-kad.
Right, רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba.
Exactly.
Big name houses at a castle. Exactly.
All right, what you say cottage.
Cottage. Come to my little college or cottage in Connecticut, right. Okay,
it's a little thing. Anyway, ואיכא נמי דלבירה קרי ליה בית. ve-ika
nami de-libira kare lei bayis. מהו דתימא, ma-hu de-teima, now, so since
I used the label בית bayis which classically means just the room,
but there it could possibly mean the whole בירה, bira, so that
combined with the dimensions, I would think you mean the whole בירה,
bira, right? So מהו דתימא, ma-hu de-teima, I might have thought כולה
זבין ליה, kula zavin lei, that that it's a possible use of
that word and you gave the dimensions, it should include everything. So
קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, מדהוה ליה למכתב, mi-de-hava lei le-michtav,
and now we finally have some rational explanation why, because when you
want to sell the whole thing, here are the here are the
key legal words you have to include when you want to sell
the whole thing. You should have
written ולא שיירית בזביני אילין כלום, ve-lo shayarti bi-zvinai illeyn klum, I
did not retain anything in what I am selling. Meaning once we're
basically what we're about to be introduced with is we're going to
have a whole פרק perek that says when you sell X, it
doesn't include A, B, C, D, E, F, G. And if you
want to do the normal thing and sell your house and sell
all the parts to it, here's the key line you have to
add to your שטר. shtar. I am selling you my house and
I am not retaining any ownership of any part of it. And
if I add those words then everything is sold. Okay, so that's
like the key line. So the basic lesson of this whole פרק
perek is include that line or there's going to be a lot
of fights about like, you know, you're not going to get what
you think you're getting. All right, so therefore if that line wasn't
included and you said בית bayis even though you gave the exterior
dimensions, that's going to force us to read the שטר shtar as
narrowly as possible. Okay, and we're going to say that the dimensions
don't dictate. The word בית bayis just refers to the narrowest definition
of the word בית. bayis. It's still bizarre because you still have
the dimensions there, but at least now it makes more sense because
we can say without that key line, be on your guard. Know
that if you don't have this key line in your document, we're
going to interpret the document as narrowly as possible. Yes.
I'm wondering if it's like in modern day if you buy an
apartment, right, and they list all the qualities of
the building, right? There's a doorman and there's a gym and there's
a pool, but it's not like you're not big, you don't get
the building.
Oh, that's interesting. Oh, I am selling you this house in the
following complex. Right, right.
That's an interesting way of thinking about it. Yeah, that fits in
with the רשב"ם Rashbam's idea, like the people know the castle they
don't know the house. But you know it's always a question about
what was the grammar of the sentence. I am selling you a
house in the castle, here are the dimensions of the castle, that's
pretty obvious, right. I am selling you a house, here are the
dimensions, sounds something different. All right, anyway, but it's at least a
helpful way to start thinking about it. All right, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Bobby, you wanted to say something earlier. No.
Okay. So it says like this, okay, שמע מינה, shema mina, so
since
you should have written that and you didn't write it, שמע מינה
שיורי שייר. shema mina shiyurei shiyer.
We see that he left stuff over for himself and we're going
to interpret it very narrowly. And now we're going to have a
very similar statement. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה המוכר שדה
לחבירו בביקעא גדולה, amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha ha-mocher sade
le-chavero be-vika gedola, I am selling you not a house, I'm selling
you my field in the middle of a big valley, right. There
are all these wheat fields and I own ten of them and
I'm selling you one of my ten fields in the middle of
this big valley of fields. Okay, so בביקעא גדולה. be-vika gedola. אף
על פי שמצר לו מצרים חיצוניים מצרים היינו דהבו ליה. af al
pi she-metzar lo metzarim hitzonim metzarim haye hivu lei.
So
again, this is like, I what can I tell you, I just
still don't understand this. But okay. Here we have, we have this
huge valley of all these fields. Now I think in Rome, Charlie
will correct me, in everything under the Roman Empire, they had a
whole very clear thing of dividing the the land in very well-defined
sort of ways or whatever. So that might make a little bit
more sense because, you know, what makes us look at this whole
valley as not one big 20 acres, what makes it look at
as there are 20 שדות sadot within here, because clearly that's what
we're going to look at it like. There are 20 שדות sadot
within this big valley. rather than just saying it's a huge twenty-acre
שדה. sadeh. Okay, and I'm going ahead and I'm selling to Eli
there this one thing. I say, "Eli, I'm going to sell you
the שדה sadeh in the middle of this one שדה. sadeh. They
own all of these fields, okay, and I'm telling you, I'm going
to sell
you this one שדה." sadeh. Eli says, "Great." We draw up the
document right here, and when I'm drawing up the document and I
say, "I am selling Eli my שדה," sadeh, and my שדה sadeh
can be is whatever is in the valley to the north of
town, and it's like two hundred אמות amot in this direction and
three hundred אמות amot in that
direction and I give him the dimensions of the whole valley. But
it says I'm selling you my שדה. sadeh. So you don't own
the, even though and I own all of the whole thing, you
only get this, you don't get the valley. Okay, and it's a
similar idea. We somehow interpret it as my שדה sadeh in this
valley of these dimensions, even though the dimensions seem to be describing
the שדה sadeh that I am selling you. Alright, so let's see
what it says. המוכר שדה לחברו בביקעה גדולה, Hamocher sadeh lechavero bebika
gedolah, אף על פי שמצר לו מצרים החיצוניים, af al pi shematzar
lo metzarim hachitzoniyim, even though you gave the outer dimensions, מצרים הרחיב
לו, metzarim hirchiv lo, you just expanded the boundaries. היכי דמי? Heichi
dami? What's the case? אילימא דקרי ליה לשדה שדה ולביקעה ביקעה, Ilima
dekari leh lesadeh sadeh ulebika bika, פשיטא. pshita. So if the word
שדה sadeh would never apply to this big expanse, it would only
apply to a very specifically
well-defined type of a plot of land, so then of course, even
though I gave you the exterior dimensions, you don't call a valley
a שדה. sadeh. פשיטא. Pshita. שדה זבין ליה ביקעה לא זבין ליה.
Sadeh zavin leh bika lo zavin leh. I sold you the שדה,
sadeh, I didn't tell you the ביקעה. bika. אלא דלביקעה נמי קרי
ליה שדה. Ela delbika nami kari leh sadeh. Okay, so let's say
sometimes I could use the word שדה sadeh to refer to this
huge expanse. So if that's true and I gave you the dimensions,
so כולה זבין ליה? kula zavin leh? So we should say he
did sell you the whole thing? No. לא צריכא, Lo tzricha, you
need it for the following case, same idea.
דאיכא דלשדה קרי ליה שדה לביקעה ביקעה. Deika del sadeh kari leh
sadeh lebika bika. There are those that call a שדה sadeh a
שדה sadeh and a ביקעה bika a ביקעה. bika. ואיכא נמי דלביקעה
קרי ליה שדה. Veika nami delbika kari leh sadeh. And then there
are those that do call the whole ביקעה bika שדה. sadeh. So
the word שדה sadeh could apply to the whole ביקעה. bika. Mostly
it applies or often it applies to just one שדה, sadeh, but
it could apply to the whole ביקעה. bika.
מהו דתימא כולה זבין ליה? Ma de teima kula zavin leh? קא
משמע לן. ka mashma lan. I might think yeah, if the word
שדה sadeh could apply to the whole thing and you gave the
dimensions, I should say you sold the whole thing? קא משמע לן
Ka mashma lan that you did not sell the whole thing. Now,
why not? You gave the dimensions, the word is relevant, why not?
דהוה ליה למכתב ליה, Dehava leh lemichtav leh, same idea, because you
should have included that key line, לא שיירי בזיבני אילין קדמאי כלום.
la shayeri bezivni ilen kadmai klum. I did not retain in my
selling of these things in front of me any ownership. That line
would have meant you interpret the שטר shtar in the maximum way.
דלא כתב ליה, Dela katav leh, and you didn't write that, שמע
מינה שיורי שיירי. shma mina shiyurei shayeri. Since you did not write
that standard line, so therefore it means you are not selling, you
are retaining ownership of yourself. So why are you giving the dimensions?
So again the רשב"ם Rashbam says, well, how do I say I
sold Eli my שדה sadeh outside of the city? Where the heck
is that שדה? sadeh? They didn't have like longitude and latitude to
give people identifying it up. So I gave him the dimensions of
the ביקעה, bika, which people could identify. They would know where the
ביקעה bika was, and that was more able to sort of to
label than it was to be able to label this. Yes, that's
the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains, yeah.
Kind of get that, they're using it like an address in a
way.
That's one way of thinking about it, right.
But what I don't understand is, is there more information identifying which
שדה sadeh in the valley is getting... It's not.
The רשב"ם Rashbam says the case was, the way the רשב"ם, Rashbam,
right, it says... So if that's all the שטר shtar said, then
we could be debating like the same, which שדה sadeh were we
talking about? So the way the רשב"ם Rashbam describes the case is
we're standing in the שדה, sadeh, and we're writing and we're drawing
up a document here in the שדה, sadeh, and the עדים eidim
are coming, and we're standing, and I'm writing in this thing, "I
am selling you this שדה sadeh here, the dimensions," and I give
you the שטר. shtar. So everybody knows where we were standing, right,
and the question is, did you mean this שדה sadeh or did
you mean that שדה? sadeh? Right.
Or or you're going to get five different guys walking around being
like, "No, we were standing here."
Right, right, I don't know what to say to you. Look, you
want to complicate it even more? תוספות Tosafot and the רשב"ם Rashbam
both say, why don't we look at what the purchase price was?
Right? Like, isn't that an obvious way to do? Look at תוספות,
Tosafot, he says, שמע מינה שיורי שיירי, shma mina shiyurei shayeri, דאי
תמא ונימא הדמים מודיעים. de-im toma venima hadamim modiyim. Let's let the
money inform us. If we have a doubt and there's obviously a
huge difference here about what the value, what the price would be,
let's look at what the price was.
כי קאמר רבי יהודה גבי המוכר את הצמד המוכר את הספינה הדבר
ידוע שאין צמד שווה מאתיים זוז. Ki ka'amar Rabi Yehuda gabi hamocher
et hatzemed hamocher et hasfina hadavar yaduah she-ein tzemed shaveh matayim zuz.
Right, if he said, "I'm selling you the yoke for two hundred
dollars,"
so a yoke doesn't mean, doesn't go for two hundred dollars. A
yoke means the two oxen. So you use the money to determine
what it means. הכא נמי נימא הדבר ידוע שאין הבית שווה כל
כך אלא כל ה- הכא נמי נימא דמי ידועין שאין בית שוה
כך כל כך אלא כל הבירה קאמר. Hacha nami neima dami yedu'in
she'ein bayit shaveh kach kol kach ela kol habira ka'amar. And the
גמרא Gemara is mov- יש לומר דהכא רבנן דפרק המוכר את הספינה
דאמרי אין דמים ראיה, yesh lomar dehacha rabanan deperek hamocher et hasfina
de'amri ein damim reaya, which doesn't actually answer the question. Like the
logic is still there. And then תוספות Tosafot has another thing. If
you skip down about four lines, he says, ועוד אומר ר"י דשמעתין
אתיא אפילו כרבי יהודה דגבי קרקע לא שייך הונאת דמים דפעמים קונה
אדם קרקע הרבה יותר ממה ששוה. Ve'od omer Ri deshmatin atya afilu
kerabi yehuda degabi karka lo shayach hona'at damim depamim koneh adam karka
harbeh yoter mima sheshava. That when it comes to land, right, that's
very hard to set a clear price on land, right, you know,
there's land speculation, people can pay a lot of money for land
more than other people were because a person thinks that they can,
I don't know, build an apartment building and develop it or who
knows, so that a locate- so people you cannot use דמים מודיעין
damim modi'in to the same degree when you're dealing with land. Nevertheless,
you would think something going a hundred times with the normal rate
maybe should be a little bit of an indication. Okay, so this
is a very hard גמרא Gemara I think to really understand
the logic behind it. Let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara. It says
like this.
וצריכא, Utzricha, you need to tell me this ruling both about the
case of the field and the case of the room of- of
the room in the castle, the chamber in the castle. דאי אשמעינן
בית משום דהא תשמישתא לחווד והא תשמישתא לחווד. De'i ashmeinan bayit mishum
deha tashmishta lechud veha tashmishta lechud. If you told me about the
house and the castle, I would say, yeah, because you know, you
don't live in two houses at the same time. So in that
type of a case, you know, I would say that if- hold
on, let me just get the rest of how this is
working. What? וצריך בית. utzrich bayit. Did I skip?
דאי אשמעינן בית משום דהא תשמישתא לחווד והא תשמישתא לחווד. de'i ashmeinan
bayit mishum deha tashmishta lechud veha tashmishta lechud. Okay, so therefore- oh,
so therefore because- oh, so therefore because- you don't live in the
whole בירה, bira, you- people live in the individual בתים batim in
the בירה, bira, nobody lives in the whole בירה. bira. So if
I say I'm selling you a בית bayit even if I give
you the dimensions of the בירה bira we should assume it means
just one living space because a בירה bira is multiple living spaces,
not- you don't live in the whole בירה. bira. Okay, so therefore
I would interpret it more narrowly. הא תשמישתא לחווד והא תשמישתא לחווד.
Ha tashmishta lechud veha tashmishta lechud. You- you live in each thing
in separately. אבל ביקא דכולא חדא תשמישתא היא, Aval bika dechula chada
tashmishta hi, but I can very easily buy this whole valley, plow
this whole field, right, it's not like- yeah, I could actually do
this as one big unit that I want to buy. So in
that type of a case אימא קני ליה. eima kani leh. Let's
say if you give the dimensions it means everything. ואי אשמעינן ביקא,
Ve'i ashmeinan bika, if you gave me the valley case, משום דלא
הוה ליה
למנצרה, mishum delo hava leh lemintzra, because in the valley there was
no other good way to identify where the field was located. סתם
Stam one field in the middle of a huge valley, the only
way, as Jenna says, a type of an address, the only way
I could identify it is I would say, you know, the valley
to the south of the city that's 500 אמות amot by 700
אמות. amot. So okay, people know where's the valley that big and
that was the way I was able to give an address and
I couldn't locate the exact field. So there we understand why I
gave the dimensions as a way of identifying it, there was no
other way of identifying the particular field. Okay, אבל ביתא דהוה
ליה למנצרה ולא מנצרה, aval beita dehava leh lemintzra velo mintzra, but
by a house I could have identified it, I could have been
specific. You know, it's the house that's painted red, it's got this
type of a door, it's the one in the northeast corner. I
didn't have to give the whole dimensions of the castle, I could
have been more specific. Okay, ולא מנצרה, velo mintzra, אימא לא קני
ליה. eima lo kani leh. Let me say so so whole thing-
וצריכא, utzricha, so you need to tell me. Of course, the more
you say that I could have been specific about the house, the
more it still leaves the question about like why are we reading
it the way we are. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says כמאן אזלא
הא דאמר רב מרי. keman azla ha de'amar rav Mari. Now we're
going to at least repeat the one thing that makes this somewhat
understandable. How's it going like that statement of רב
מרי rav Mari ברה דבת שמואל, bra debat Shmuel, the- or-
yeah, it says ברה brei which is the son, I don't understand
the- the
side- the side says ברא. bra. ברא bra is a daughter.
No, he is the son of the daughter of שמואל. Shmuel. So
I don't understand the switch between ברה, brei, maybe it's the possessive,
the son of a woman is ברא. bra. It must be the
Aramaic grammar. The ברה brei is the son of a man and
the ברא bra is the son of a woman.
ברא Bra is her son.
Right, ברתא barta is daughter so ברא bra is her son. Right.
Okay. So אל הא דאמר רב מרי ברה דבת שמואל, el ha
de'amar rav Mari bra debat Shmuel, so he
wrote about what- using a-
yeah, why there is- why their- her mother was an idolator?
Yeah, yeah, the father- right.
So רב מרי rav Mari who- anyway, רב מרי rav Mari the
son- the son of the daughter of שמואל, Shmuel, בר שילא Bar
Shila or not בר שילא, Bar Shila, anyway משמיה דאביי, mishmeih de'Abaye,
the statement was האי מאן דמזבין ליה מידי לחבריה, hai man demazbin
leh midi lechavereih, if you sell something to your friend, צריך למיכתב
ליה, tzarich lemichtav leh, this makes everything more understandable, the standard
thing you have to include in every bill of sale is לא
שיירית בזביני אילין קדמאי כלום. lo shayerit bizvini ilin kadmai klum. I
am not retaining ownership of anything of what- of what is being
sold. And if you don't write that, you're at your own risk
about that we're going to interpret the שטר shtar much more narrowly.
All right. Now, by the way, תוספות Tosafot discusses maybe part of
the reason we're going to interpret the שטר shtar narrowly has to-
this whole idea of חזקה. chazaka. Right, it's my property. property, I
was in possession, that's a little funny. Is it a חזקה? chazakah?
But you have a שטר. shtar. A שטר shtar is like עדות,
eidut, testimony that you took possession of it. But the question is
what do the words in the שטר shtar mean? So it's an
interesting הלכה halachah question. Who has the burden of proof with a
שטר shtar that the terms are ambiguous? Okay. And even if let's
say they incline towards one side. So this makes it sound like
well since I was the one initially in possession, if I have
a clear line that says I'm selling everything, that's yours. But if
I don't have that clear line and I started in possession, we're
going to interpret it more narrowly, sort of assume give me the
benefit of the doubt that I didn't sell certain things. That seems
to be the logic behind this. Okay. So if you don't have
that line, you're at your own risk. Okay. כמאן כרב נחמן. Keman
keRav Nachman. That's going like Rav Nachman. Rav Nachman's statement that even
when you give the boundaries, you don't sell the whole thing, could
only make sense if we assume that you're supposed to be including
this line. Then you don't include the line, you'll have to live
with the consequences. Okay. אמר רבא בר אבוה. Amar Rava bar Avuha.
Now we're going to switch gears because I think we were all
not grappling with understanding what the גמרא Gemara was saying but understanding
why it made sense. Okay. Anyway. אמר רבא בר אבוה. Amar Rava
bar Avuha. So says רבא בר אבוה. Rava bar Avuha. ההוא דאמר
ליה לחבריה. Hahu de'amar lei lechavreih. Somebody said to his friend, ארעא
דרבי חייא מזבננא לך. Ar'a deRabbi Chiya mezavanna lach. I just bought
some land from Rabbi Chiya. I'm going to sell you the land
of Rabbi Chiya. And we write up a שטר. shtar. Okay. Dov
sold to David there the land of Rabbi Chiya that Dov had
purchased. Okay. Now הוו ליה תרתי ארעתא דהוו מיתקרין דבי חייא, Havu
lei tarti ar'ata dehavu mitkeryan debei Chiya, the only thing was he
had two plots of land which were called the land of Chiya.
He had bought them at separate times, they were in two separate
locations. Okay. So the הלכה halachah is, אמר רב אשי חדא אמר
ליה תרתי לא אמר ליה, Amar Rav Ashi chada amar lei tarti
lo amar lei, if you said I am selling you the land
and not the lands,
so that means only one plot and if there are two separate
plots then you can't prove then I did
not tell you
both, I only sold you one and then the רשב"ם Rashbam takes
it further. And if there's a debate which one, המוציא מחברו עליו
הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah. I have the right to interpret which
one it was that I sold you. So again at least that
does seem to be a
theme
here that even in the presence of a שטר, shtar, if there's
some ambiguity, it weighs in favor of the previous owner, of the
one that was מוחזק. muchzak. Now, תרתי ארעתא דהוו מיתקרין. Tarti ar'ata
dehavu mitkeryan. Okay. חדא אמר ליה תרתי לא אמר ליה. Chada amar
lei tarti lo amar lei. He said one, not two. אי אמר
ליה ארעתא, Ei amar lei ar'ata, if somebody said I am selling
you the ארעתא ar'ata which is what was the word before? ארעא.
Ar'a. So I don't know exactly is ארעתא ar'ata lands? Is it
plural? Wait. Wait. הוו ליה ארעתא. Havu lei ar'ata. ארעתא, Ar'ata, doesn't
ארעתא ar'ata with the אלף alef at the end mean the land
and ארעא ar'a means a piece of land? They have all the
lands. All the well, that's begging I yeah that but I'm not
sure just grammatically what is the difference between ארעא ar'a and ארעתא?
ar'ata? When it says תרתי tarti then it says ארעתא. ar'ata. Oh
that's a good point. Oh that's a good point. So it just
it is in the plural. So Jenna points out that just grammatically,
yeah I was going to check that, thank you Jenna. It says
when it says if you sell ארעתא דבי חייא ar'ata debei Chiya
when it says חדא chada where was it? It says חדא אמר
ליה תרתי לא אמר chada amar lei tarti lo amar wait no
where did it say ארעתא? ar'ata? Oh. הוו ליה תרתי ארעתא. Havu
lei tarti ar'ata. Oh that's a good point. Right. When it said
he had two plots of land, it used ארעתא. ar'ata. So ארעתא
ar'ata seems to be the plural. So therefore, so based on thank
you Jenna, so based on that if you said אי אמר ליה
ארעתא סתמא, ei amar lei ar'ata stama, so if you just said
I'm selling you the lands of Rabbi Chiya, so מיעוט ארעתא שתים.
mi'ut ar'ata shtayim. So the minimum is two. But let's say you
had five plots of land and you said I'm selling you the
land. So the lands still just means two, it doesn't mean all
the land. So if you, so okay, it doesn't mean one, but
it doesn't mean all. It means two. אי אמר ליה כל ארעתא,
Ei amar lei kol ar'ata, I'm selling you all the lands, כל
ארעתא דאית ליה kol ar'ata de'is lei then it includes everything. לבר
מבוסתנא ופרדיסא. Lavar mibustana ufardisa. It doesn't include orchards and gardens. Okay.
ארעא סתם Ar'a stam sort of means like land for like fields,
for growing wheat and grain. You would use a different word for
orchards and gardens. So if you say I'm selling you all the
lands, it means all the wheat fields but it doesn't mean the
gardens and the orchards. אי אמר ליה זירא, Ei amar lei zeira,
but if you say זירא zeira which is another word, fields or
something of that nature, that word is generic enough to include any
type of cultivated land, אפילו בבוסתנא ופרדיסא afilu bebustana ufardisa even orchards
and gardens. לבר, Lavar, but the one thing that it doesn't include
is מבתי ועבדי. mibatei ve'avdei. Even though you say the lands, land
does not mean my house. Land still means like land, that word
זירא zeira whatever it means in Aramaic still means like cultivated land,
land used for growing things. It doesn't mean slaves even though slaves
are attached to land in some way and it doesn't mean homes
even though obviously homes are built on land. It's a different type
on land. אי אמר ליה נכסי, Ei amar lei nichsei, if you
say I'm selling you all of my property, אפילו בתי ועבדי afilu
batei ve'avdei then even slaves and houses. Okay. So at least the
end was a little bit more understandable. Wait, continue, it says I
am selling you my land and property, what do you mean? He
says that he is including the doors to it. Correct. But excluding
his houses and Canaanite slaves. Right, that's what we just said. Oh,
then I missed that. Okay, have a wonderful day. יישר כח. Yasher
koach. כל טוב. Kol tuv.